Guide to the Whitener Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Whitener Family Papers
1945-2000
RG 151
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(6 boxes)
Letters, photographs, and collected material, primarily from the late 1940s and early 1950s document the work of the Whiteners and the history of Christianity in Hunan Province, China and in Hong Kong. The elder Whiteners, Sterling W. and Marie, were missionaries in Yochow, Hunan Province, China from 1919 to 1948, serving under the Reformed Church in the United States and the Evangelical and Reformed Church. Their son, Sterling H. Whitener, and his wife Barbara were missionaries in Hunan Province from 1946 to 1950 and in Hong Kong from the early 1950s to 1967.
Whitener, Sterling Hegnauer, 1921-
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Whitener family.
Biographical / Historical
Sterling Wilfong Whitener was born in 1894 in North Carolina. He married Marie Hegnauer in 1919 and they left for China that year, serving as missionaries first under the Reformed Church in the U.S. and later under the Evangelical and Reformed Church. Following language study in Nanking, the Whiteners were stationed in Yochow, Hunan Province. SWW was assigned to evangelistic work and Marie worked with a women's Bible school. Following their furlough in 1924 the Whiteners returned to Yochow but in 1927 political disturbances forced their evacuation to Shanghai and then to the United States. where SWW served three churches in Thomasville, NC. From 1928 to 1934 the Whiteners again served in Yochow. Due to the political situation, SWW worked with famine relief during the floods of 1930 while the family was evacuated to Shanghai for six months. SWW also organized relief programs for refugees fleeing fighting. Following furlough in 1934, the Whiteners returned to Yochow. During 1939 to 1941 the Whiteners were evacuated to Yuanling in western Hunan Province due to air raids. Marie was in Shanghai during 1940 so that the children could attend Shanghai American School. From 1941 to 1946 the Whiteners were on an extended furlough in North Carolina, unable to return to China because of war conditions. They returned to Yoyang (Yochow) in 1946 and Marie died in Hankow in 1947. SWW returned to the United States in 1948 and died in North Carolina in 1950.
Sterling Hegnauer Whitener was born in China in 1921, son of Sterling and Marie. After receiving a B.A. from Catawba College and a M. Div. from Yale Divinity School, SHW and his wife, Barbara Brown Whitener, joined his parents in Yoyang, Hunan Province in 1946, serving under the Evangelical and Reformed Church. After one year of educational work, SHW was involved in evangelistic work and acted as treasurer for the mission. SHW and BBW stayed in Hunan until September 1950. Following SHW's study for an S.T.M. degree at Yale Divinity School, they returned to mission work in Hong Kong. SHW assisted refugees at the Rennie's Mill Camp and worked with the Hong Kong Council, Church of Christ in China, organizing a Social Welfare Department for the Church. He also served as an interim director of Church World Service and helped found Chung Chi College. After taking his MSW degree while on furlough in 1965, he taught at the University of Hong Kong until 1967.
Scope and Contents
I. Correspondence, 1946-1995.
II. Notes and Writings of SHW, 1945-1972, n.d.
III. Collected Material, 1946-1995, n.d.
IV. Biographical Documentation, 1947-2000, n.d.
These papers provide valuable documentation of the issues, events, and transactions surrounding two areas: 1) the transfer of power from a Western mission agency to the Church of Christ in China and 2) the Church and Communism in China from 1948 to 1952. They also provide information about rural work in Hunan Province and church social service work in Hong Kong.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1946-1995
II. Notes and Writings of SHW, 1945-1972, n.d.
III. Collected Material, 1946-1995, n.d.
IV. Biographical Documentation, 1947-2000,n.d.
Missions -- China; Whitener, Sterling Hegnauer, 1921-; Evangelical and Reformed Church -- Missions -- China
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Sterling W. and Marie Whitener
    - Family letters, 1946 May-1949 Jul (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - General correspondence with Board of International Missions, Hartman, and others, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sterling H. and Barbara Whitener
    - Family correspondence
      - Letters to/from brothers and Sterling W. Whitener, 1946 Oct-1953 May (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
    - General correspondence
      - B, incl. Beeken, Beck (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Board of International Missions (see also: Gregory and Hartman), 1946 Dec - 1965 Nov (Box 1, Folder 10-16)
      - C-D (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Daniels, Bill and Jane, 1947 Apr-1951 Oct (Box 1, Folder 18-21)
      - E-F, incl. Elinor, Faucett (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Farnam, Vernon, 1949 Sep-1951 Aug (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
      - G, 1950 Feb (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Gregory, Paul and Kit (see also International Board of Missions), 1947 Aug-1967 Sep (Box 2, Folder 26-30)
      - H (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Hartman, Ward (see also International Board of Missions), 1948 Mar -1952 May (Box 2, Folder 32-39)
      - I-K (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - L, incl. Li, Liu (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Latourette, Kenneth Scott, 1946 Aug-1953 Jan (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - Leonard / Liu Zhongcheng, 1989 Oct-1995 Nov (Box 2, Folder 43-46)
      - M (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - O-P, incl. Price (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - S, incl Stange, Stowe (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - T-Y, incl. Whitehead, Yearick (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Ziegler, Reynold and Ann, 1947 Apr-1950 Feb (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Fragments (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - Chinese language correspondence (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Circular letters
      - Circular letters sent by Sterling H. and Barbara Whitener (Box 3, Folder 53-55)
- Notes and Writings by SHW, Series II
  - Student paper: "Chinese Church Architecture", 1945 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Student paper: "The Growth of Church Self-Government in North Hunan", 1951 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Student paper: "The Interpretation of History in Chinese Christianity", 1952 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - "A Program for Rural Improvement for Yoyang, Hunan, China", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - "A young man returns home to marry his cousin" and others (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Notes on Chinese Communism (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - "Chinese Communist Attitude Toward Religion and Treatment of Religious Groups", ca. 1951 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Sermon, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - "The Future of Undergraduate Social Worker Education and the Role of the B.A. Worker", 1972 (Box 3, Folder 65)
- Collected Material, Series III
  - Writings of others
    - Lindbeck, Luce, Niebuhr, 1946-1951 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Grace Liu, Daniel Bays, Leonard, 1954-1994 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Papers re. Christianity and Communism, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Miscellaneous publications
    - Publications of the Committee for a Democratic Far Eastern Policy, 1950, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - English language pamphlets by Mao Tse-tung and Wu Hsiu-chuan, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Chinese language pamphlets with English titles; "Karl Marx or Jesus Christ" by V. R. Edman; " Communism's Three-fold Challenge to the Christian Church" by S. Boyle; "The Social and Economic Responsibility of the Church" by J. Vos, ca. 1949-1950, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Chung Hwa English Fortnightly - 6 issues (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Chinese language reports, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Hoy Hospital - 90th anniversary booklet, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Huping College - 20th anniversary booklet, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Related to mission work in China
    - Financial records and reports, 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Minutes and reports, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Re. Hunan District, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Re. Huping Middle School, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Related to mission work in Hong Kong
    - Minutes of Social Welfare Committee, CCC, Hong Kong District, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Miscellaneous reports, 1949-1966 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Children's work (Grampian Village, Homantin Faith Hope Club), 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Refugee village biographies, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Re. social welfare work in Hong Kong, 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 84-85)
    - Re. education strategies, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Plays and pageants, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Scripts to accompany slide and film presentations (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - News clippings and items, 1956-1995 (Box 4, Folder 89-90)
- Biographical Documentation, Series IV
  Scope and Contents
  Material in missing box 5; consult with Special Collections staff.
  - Biographical information re. Sterling W. and Marie H. Whitener, incl. summary of ministry and memorial tributes
  - Biographical information re. Sterling H. and Barbara Whitener, incl. certificates from YDS and University of North Carolina
  - Re. "Mission Roots" tour to China led by SHW, 1992
  - Re. China tours led by SHW, 1996, 2000
  - Re. Fulbright year, 1973-1974
  - Photographs and slides, incl. Hunan Synod meeting and re. mission work, 1947-1950, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 96)